Gang-du!
康斗
Lee Gang-du!
李康斗
My life may only get worse.
我的生活可能只會更糟
And, if it does, it's better to be alone.
要是那樣，我應該獨自一個人
So…
所以…
Run away.
我逃跑
GALAXY INN
（銀河客棧）
Oh, my goodness! Who's that?
天啊，這是誰？
Excuse me.
不好意思？
Miss.
小姐
Why are you sleeping here?
妳為什麼睡在這裡？
This room is occupied. Who are you?
這個房間已經租出去了，妳是誰？
I'm sorry. I came to get my bag and fell asleep.
很抱歉，我來拿我的包包，然後睡著了
Are you the girl hanging out with Gang-du recently?
妳是那個跟康斗一起出去玩的女生嗎？
Sorry?
妳說什麼？
Oh. Yes.
沒錯
He won't be home for several days.
他有好幾天都不會在家
For that long?
要那麼久？
He insisted on working on a boat even in this cold weather,
他堅持要在這種冷天到船上工作
knowing full well that Sang-man would look for him.
明明知道相萬會到處找他
Ma'am.
太太
Has Gang-du been living here long?
康斗住在這裡很久了嗎？
Oh, yes. He has.
是啊，住很久了
Probably seven years. Why do you ask?
大概七年了，妳為什麼問？
He has a sister. I wonder why he lives alone.
他有個妹妹，我很好奇他為什麼一個人住
Looks like his sister was raised properly.
看起來他妹妹有被好好地撫養長大
But, good gracious, he was…
但是，天哪，他…
Oh, dear. When he first came here, he was nothing but skin and bones.
天啊，他第一次來這裡時骨瘦如柴
He was just like a poor beggar.
就像個可憐的乞丐
But he started to live like a decent person here.
但是他在這裡開始過像樣的生活
Children struggle a lot when their mom isn't around.
沒有媽媽的孩子生活都很艱難
They need their mom.
他們需要他們的媽媽
Goodness. What would happen to Sang-man if I weren't around?
天哪，要是我不在了，相萬會怎麼樣呢？
-I'll get going. -Okay.
-我要回去了 -好的
Excuse me.
不好意思
Isn't this bus stop absurd?
這個公車站很荒謬，不是嗎？
Look, "Space S Mall."
妳看，“S空間商場”
That disappeared ages ago.
幾年前就消失了
The wind is blowing! Let's hurry!
起風了，大家都趕快
Do you have a death wish?
你找死還是怎樣？
What if you get caught in the net? Don't get so close to that!
萬一被漁網纏住怎麼辦？ 你不能太靠近漁網
The deceased aren't the only victims.
死者並不是唯一的受害者
How will they compensate for the painful lives
那些活在痛苦中的人呢？
of the ones who had to live on?
他們要怎麼補償他們？
You look very distressed.
妳看起來很憂傷
When you're distressed, don't be alone. Come to my prayer meeting instead.
憂傷的時候，不要獨自一個人 來我的禮拜堂吧
Even though you're currently in misery, you can be saved if you believe in God.
就算妳是在苦難中 只要相信上帝，妳就可以得救
God will never give you more than you can handle.
上帝永遠不會給妳妳承受不了的事
-With us-- -What about the pain I can't handle?
-跟我們一起… -如果是我承受不了的痛苦呢？
Prayer will help you overcome that.
禱告可以幫妳戰勝痛苦
What about the people who live in pain all their lives, unable to do so?
如果是那些生活在痛苦中 沒辦法這麼做的人呢？
Sorry?
妳說什麼？
What about the people who gave up and died? What can God do for them?
如果是在痛苦中死去的人呢？ 上帝可以幫他們做什麼？
GOD INVITES YOU WITH LOVE
（上帝以愛邀請你）
I won't believe in him.
我不會相信祂的
We fill the position with day laborers.
我們請了臨時工來填補空缺
But they easily quit after training or skip work.
但是受訓之後 他們很快就不幹了，或是翹班
For me, it's tough without Gang-du.
我覺得沒有康斗，工作很費勁
Well, he may look like a good-for-nothing fellow,
那傢伙可能看起來像個廢柴
but he did his job well.
但是他把他的工作做得很好
So I'm wondering if you can ask him to come back.
所以我在想，你能不能叫他回來工作
-No, I can't. -Oh, I see.
-不，我沒辦法 -那我知道了
He won't come back.
他不回來了
I see.
我知道了
These are over there.
這些是在那裡
I heard you helped us reinspect the ground.
我聽說妳幫我們重新勘查過地面
I didn't do it for you.
我不是為了你做的
I also like to be sure.
我也想要確認一下
I knew you'd go ahead with it despite opposition from Cheongyu.
雖然清州反對你這麼做 但是我知道你會繼續
Anyway, thank you.
總之，謝謝妳
Isn't expectation scarier than opposition?
期待不是比反對更可怕嗎？
I'll support you as much as I can.
我會儘量支持你
You can push me away when it comes to private matters.
如果是私事，你可以把我推開
But when it comes to work, you'll need me.
但如果跟工作有關，你會需要到我
GROUND INSPECTION REPORT
（地面勘查報告）
I can't drink soju.
我不能喝燒酒
Think of it like medicine. It'll help you nap for a few hours.
這就像安眠藥，可以幫你小睡幾個鐘頭
-Is it good? -Yeah.
-好喝嗎？ -好喝
What's good about it?
有什麼好喝的？
This.
這個
ASK YOURSELF ONE THING BEFORE BED
（睡覺前，問妳自己一個問題）
I REALLY LIKE…
（我真的喜歡…）
For goodness sake!
看在老天的份上
WIll you stop doing that?
妳可以不要一直嘆氣嗎？
Fine. Let's go over it again.
好吧，我們再聊一次吧
Your memory suddenly came back after ten years.
妳的記憶十年後，突然回來了
And Gang-du was in it. That's it, right?
記憶裡有康斗，就這樣，對吧？
Do you remember anything else?
妳還記得別的事嗎？
Only bits and pieces.
只有零碎和片段的記憶
But I'm positive that I saw Gang-du there.
但是我很確定我在那裡看到康斗
What are you doing here? Go ask him yourself.
妳在這裡幹嘛？去問他呀
I can't see him now.
我現在見不到他
His cell phone must work fine.
他的手機一定沒問題
And you can go anywhere in this tiny country in a day.
更何況在這小國家 妳可以在一天內去到任何地方
Why can't you see him?
妳為什麼見不到他？
This is not good.
這樣不好
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Everything is about timing.
一切都關乎時機
You missed each other. Isn't that a sign you two aren't meant to be?
你們錯過了彼此 那不就是在暗示你們不該是一對嗎？
Wan-jin.
-婉珍 -我知道我暗戀過他
just because I had a crush on him.
那不是我不耐煩的原因
The person who stands by you when you're desperate is the one for you.
在妳絕望無助時 站在妳身邊支持妳的，才是妳要的男人
Think about it.
妳好好想想吧
Oh, what question should she ask?
天哪，她該問什麼問題呢？
Oh, dear. What should she ask herself?
天啊，她該問自己什麼問題呢？
I think you're right.
我覺得妳說得對
What?
什麼？
I think I'm anxious because I'm not by his side.
我覺得我焦慮是因為我不在他身邊
That's right. That's the reason.
沒錯了，就是這個原因
Hey, I think you misunderstood--
我覺得妳誤會…
Thank you, Wan-jin.
謝謝妳，婉珍
Hey. Oh, my.
喂，天啊
My goodness.
我的天啊
What should I do with her?
我該拿她怎麼辦呢？
TO WAKE UP NEXT TO?
（妳想要在誰的身旁醒來？）
You're back.
你回來啦
Isn't it yummy?
是不是很好吃？
-Why are you looking at me like that? -Nothing.
-為什麼那樣看我？ -沒什麼
Shall we go to Eulsukdo Island next week? Let's go see migratory birds.
我們下週去乙淑島好嗎？我們去看候鳥吧
You can also see splendid reeds--
妳還可以看到絢麗的蘆葦田…
Is it also a place you went to with your first love?
那也是你跟初戀去過的地方嗎？
Or do you just want to take me along as a replacement?
還是你只是想帶我去，當作是替代品？
Jeez.
天啊
I don't believe stories about first love.
我不相信初戀的故事
It's not true you miss or care for your first love.
説你是想念或在乎你的初戀情人 那都不是真話
You've become materialistic,
是因為你變得很現實了
so you just miss your old self who was young and innocent.
所以你只是很懷念過去 那個年輕又無知的自己
Why are you so cranky today?
妳今天為什麼那麼怪裡怪氣的？
You said the other day that you'd fire someone. Was that Gang-du?
那天你說你炒了一個人的魷魚 那個人是康斗嗎？
Is that the reason?
就是為了這件事嗎？
I thought you were at least a good judge of character.
我以為你至少很會看人
Why on earth are you doing this to me today?
妳今天為什麼這樣對我？
Did I do something wrong? I had my reasons!
我做錯了什麼嗎？我有我的理由
What were the reasons? That you hate him?
理由是什麼？是你討厭他嗎？
Where are you going?
妳要去哪裡？
-I have a customer. -What about me?
-我有客人 -那我呢？
I'll send you another girl.
我會安排另一個女生過來
Have a nice time.
祝你玩得愉快
What the hell does he mean to you?
他對妳來說到底是什麼？
Who is that jerk to you?
那個混蛋是妳什麼人？
He's my savior.
他是我的救星
Hey, dude.
喂，老兄
You could have a stroke if you sleep out here.
睡在甲板上會中風的
Why are you struggling to sleep?
你為什麼睡不著？
Sleeping when you can is also your job.
儘可能睡覺也是你的工作
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
Boy, we'd be excited if we caught some fish.
天啊，要是有捕到魚，我們會很興奮
But we haven't caught any for days.
但我們好幾天都一無所獲
Goodness. It's so exhausting.
天啊，只讓人精疲力盡
It won't rain tomorrow, so we may be able to catch some.
明天不會下雨 所以我們可能會捕到一些魚
It doesn't matter if it rains.
下不下雨不重要
At sea, wind is scarier than rain.
在海上，颳風比下雨還要可怕
Goodness. The waves tell me that it'll be pretty windy again tomorrow.
天啊，海浪告訴我，明天又會是颳風天
Both fishing and life are all about timing.
捕魚和人生的關鍵是時機
If you miss the timing,
錯過了時機
you never know when you'll get another chance.
你就永遠不會知道 什麼時候才會有下一次機會
We chose the wrong time.
我們選錯時機了
Granny.
老奶奶
Oh, dear.
親愛的
SANHO PUBLIC BATH
（珊瑚公共澡堂）
Jeez, I don't know why I crave this when I come to a bathhouse.
天哪，不知道為什麼 我來澡堂時就會很想喝這個
Is Gang-du out on a boat?
康斗坐船出海了嗎？
That punk.
那個小混混
He always does things that's hard on his body.
他總去做非常辛苦的工作 他離開前，妳有見到他嗎？
I was late.
我去得太晚了
It happens.
這是常有的事
You're too young to be discouraged by such a thing.
妳還年輕，別為這種事感到氣餒
Did you know that Gang-du and I were both in the accident?
妳知道我和康斗一起被困嗎？
What's the use in talking about the past?
談論過去有什麼用？
I didn't know. Like a fool.
我居然傻傻的不知道
I don't know whether I really can't remember
不知道我是真的忘了
or if I just want to live in peace.
還是我只想要平靜地生活
I have no idea.
完全搞不清楚
Why are you blaming yourself again?
妳幹嘛又責備自己呢？
You got hurt too. It was an awful accident.
妳也受傷了，那是個很悲慘的意外
For some reason, I feel like I'm doing something wrong.
不知道為什麼 我總覺得自己做錯了什麼事
When a squirrel gets two acorns, it puts one of them in its mouth
松鼠要是找到兩顆橡果，牠會把一顆吃掉
and stores the other one in the ground for winter.
把另一顆埋在土裡存起來準備過冬
Do you know that?
妳知道嗎？
They work so hard for it. But they're fools.
牠們這麼辛勞儲存食物，但牠們是蠢蛋
They can't eat it because they forget where they stored it.
結果牠們吃不到 因為牠們忘了把橡果藏在哪裡了
-What a waste. -It is a waste.
-好可惜 -是很可惜
But the interesting thing is,
但是有趣的是
the acorn buried for the entire winter
埋在土裡的橡果度過整個冬天後
sprouts, becomes a tree, and forms a forest.
發芽了，然後長成一棵樹 最後變成一座森林
That's a fortunate thing for us.
對我們來說，這是一件幸運的事
Forgetting about the pain is also a good way to get over it.
忘記痛苦也是一種擺脫痛苦的好辦法
Who knows how it will turn out later?
誰知道結果會是怎樣的呢？
There are always ups and downs.
人生總有起起伏伏
Oh, right. What brings you here?
對了，妳怎麼來了？
I came here by taxi to take a bath.
我坐計程車來這裡泡澡
I don't think I've seen you before. Do you live in this area?
我好像沒見過妳，妳住這附近嗎？
No, I don't. It's just that I haven't been to a bathhouse in a long time.
不，不是，我只是很久沒去澡堂了
Had I known sooner, I would've come more often.
要是我早一點知道，我會經常來
Come often from now on.
從現在開始常來吧
The lady who works here is very good at scrubbing.
我們的搓澡師傅手藝非常棒
-Really? Shall I get the service then? -Sure. It's very refreshing.
-真的？那我該去搓澡了嗎？ -當然，會讓妳感覺非常清爽
Are you okay with the length?
這個長度可以嗎？
I'll dry your hair after you take your bath.
泡完澡我再幫妳吹頭髮
Auntie!
阿姨
-Yes? -You have a customer.
-怎麼了？ -有客人
Come on in. Soak yourself first.
請進，先泡澡吧
-Oh, dear. -Thank you.
-天哪 -謝謝妳
-Go on in. -I need to get undressed.
-進去吧 -我得先脫衣服
-Where's Granny? -She's getting scrubbed.
-老奶奶呢？ -她要搓澡
How do you know her?
妳怎麼認識她的？
She's a friend of a friend. Something like that.
她算是一個朋友的朋友吧
Is she sick or something?
-她生病了嗎？ -怎麼了？
It felt like she was preparing herself.
我感覺她好像在為自己做準備
I have a bad feeling.
我有不好的感覺
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
I get that feeling sometimes when I work.
我有時候在工作時，會有那種感覺
-Hey! -What's wrong?
-不好了 -怎麼了？
-Auntie. -The old lady!
-阿姨 -那個老太太
Hurry! Oh, my goodness!
快，我的天啊
Hey, the net is stuck! Bring us the diving suits!
喂，漁網卡住了，去拿潛水衣
Diving suits! Hurry!
潛水衣，快點
Bring us the rope!
去拿繩子
-For goodness sake. -Are you okay?
-我的天啊 -你沒事吧？
-Gosh. -For goodness sake.
-天啊 -我的天啊
-Granny. -I'm fine.
-老太太 -我沒事
I was in the hot bath for too long, so I just got dizzy.
我泡太久熱水澡了，我只是有點暈
It wasn't the first time.
這不是第一次了
Please get a checkup.
請妳去檢查一下吧
-I said I'm fine. -No, you're not.
-我說了我很好 -不，妳不好
I told you to wait while I admit you.
我叫妳等我安排妳住院
-Let's go. -You'll die if you don't get treatment.
-走吧 -不治療的話，妳會死掉的
No one knows when the brain tumor will kill you.
誰都不知道腦瘤什麼時候會要了妳的命
The sooner you get treated--
妳越快接受治療…
Do you know what most people die of?
妳知道大部分的人都是怎麼死的嗎？
Cancer? An accident? Suicide? It's none of them.
癌症？意外？自殺？都不是
It's poverty.
是貧窮
The poor can't afford to get medical treatment.
窮人負擔不起醫療費用
Some do hard labor to overcome poverty, but they die in an accident.
有的人去做粗重的工作來擺脫貧困 但是他們都死於意外
And some commit suicide, sick of being poor.
有些人會自殺，因為受不了窮困的生活
They die of poverty.
他們是因為貧困而死的
It's a mere tumor. It doesn't scare me at all. Step aside.
這只不過是顆腦瘤，我一點都不怕，讓開
The tumor is on the hypothalamus.
那顆瘤長在腦部的下視丘
If she gets surgery, she may lose all her memory.
如果動手術，她有可能會失去所有記憶
That's why she's doing nothing.
-所以她什麼都不想做 -動手術就會好起來嗎？
Because she's elderly, I can't say anything for sure.
因為她很老了，我也不敢保證
Does Gang-du know?
康斗知道嗎？
She told me not to tell him.
她叫我不要告訴他
You should tell him.
妳應該告訴他
He'll be heartbroken if he finds out too late.
要是他太晚才知道，他會心碎的
She keeps insisting, so I can't do anything.
她很堅持，所以我不能做什麼
I was there too.
當時我也在那裡
In the collapsed mall.
在那個坍塌的商場裡
Things that happen out of the blue frighten me.
我很害怕突然發生的事
I'm sure Gang-du feels the same way.
我相信康斗也一樣
You have to tell Gang-du.
妳必須告訴康斗
I really hate things like this.
我真的很討厭做這種事
Hey. Go get me the fisheries log.
喂，去幫我拿捕魚日誌
Okay.
好的
Hey, Kim! Fill that up with ice! Why are you saving it?
喂，金，用冰塊填滿它 你為什麼要節省冰塊？
Those containers too!
那些魚盤也一樣
Go check the barge conditions.
去檢查駁船的情況
Hurry, for goodness sake!
快點，看在老天的份上
What?
怎麼了？
Right now? How, all of a sudden?
現在嗎？怎麼這麼突然？
Hey! Are you crazy?
喂，你瘋了嗎？
-If you leave now-- -The timing!
-你現在離開的話… -時機
What?
什麼？
I can't miss the timing!
我不能錯失了時機
MOKSAN CITY HOSPITAL
（木山市立醫院）
It's called glioblastoma, the most malignant tumor.
那是膠質母細胞瘤，是侵襲性最強的腫瘤
It's become bigger since the last exam.
上一次檢查後，它變更大了
It's growing too fast.
它長得太快了
If her surgery goes well, she may be able to live another year--
要是手術順利，她或許可以多活一年
Screw the complicated words.
直接跟我說就好了
She's going to die?
她會死嗎？
Tell me.
告訴我
What will you do with all that money?
妳留著那些錢要幹嘛？
You punk. Make some noise when you come in.
你這個小混混，進來時出點聲啦
Goodness.
天哪
Oh, dear.
天啊
I heard you're dying.
我聽說妳要死了
You taking all that money with you?
那些錢妳要帶走嗎？
Yes, I will. Are you envious?
對，我會，是壞消息嗎？
Hey, I've earned all this by myself.
這些都是我自己賺來的
I'm no longer hard up for money.
我再也不用過沒錢的日子了
I'll go and brag to my husband about it.
我會去跟我的丈夫炫耀
You can't go anywhere!
妳哪兒都不能去
Be quiet. I'm not dying right at this minute.
安靜，我又不是這一刻就會死
I heard you're sick, but you seem to be full of energy.
我聽說妳生病了，看來妳還很有活力
If you're going to brag,
要是妳想炫耀
make more money before you go.
賺多一點再走
How can you laugh?
妳還笑得出來？
What's the use of crying?
哭有什麼用？
Gang-du.
康斗
Do you think the dead go to heaven
你覺得人死後上了天堂
the way that they looked at the time of their deaths?
他們的樣貌會一直保持在 他們死去時的那個樣子嗎？
I don't know. I've never died before. How would I know?
不知道，我又沒死過，我怎麼會知道？
-Why do you ask? -It's just unfair.
-妳為什麼問？ -只是覺得不公平
I'm going to see my husband in heaven.
我就要跟我老公在天堂裡見面了
But he'd look just as handsome as he did when he was 30.
但他會看起來跟他30歲時一樣帥
I'm an old woman with a wrinkled face, so I'd be embarrassed to see him.
而我是個滿臉皺紋的老女人 所以我會不好意思見到他
That's good. It serves you right. I'm sure he's been cheating on you.
那樣很好，妳活該 我相信他一直都在劈腿
You're talking nonsense.
你在胡說八道
I'm sure he's already remarried.
我相信他已經結婚了
Surrounded by women, he wouldn't even remember you.
被很多女人包圍，他根本不會記得妳
Even if you went there, he'd reject you.
就算妳去了那裡，他也會拒絕你
So don't go.
所以妳不要走
Don't go…
別走
and stay here with me.
留下來陪我
Why?
-為什麼？ -什麼？
Just to see if you're okay.
只是想知道你好不好
I'm okay.
我沒事
GALAXY INN
（銀河客棧）
Oh, my. When did you come back?
天哪，你什麼時候回來的？
Oh. Just now.
剛剛回來的
-Did you eat? -Yes.
-吃了嗎？ -吃了
You don't look like you did.
看起來還沒吃
-Go down. I just need to warm up the soup. -No. It's okay.
-你下去吧，我把湯熱一下就好了 -不用了，沒關係
-Where's Sang-man? -While you were gone, he was…
-相萬呢？ -你不在的時候，他…
I gave him a pill to go to sleep.
我給他吃了藥去睡覺了
It's okay to be late with the rent,
房租遲繳沒關係
so don't go far to do hard labor.
所以你不要去那麼遠做粗重的工作
Goodness. What is this smell? It smells sweaty and fishy.
天啊，這是什麼味？ 聞起來都是汗臭和魚腥味
Take off your clothes and wash up.
把衣服脫掉去洗洗
Gosh, it stinks.
天啊，臭死了
How can a person smell like this? How dirty.
一個人怎麼可以這麼臭呢？髒死了
Why are you still here?
妳為什麼還在這裡？
I've been waiting for you.
我在等你
Why? Do you have something to say?
為什麼？有話要說嗎？
If not, forget it.
如果沒有，就算了吧
I do.
有
The mall collapse.
商場坍塌，你在事故發生時 看到我了，對嗎？
We were together, right?
我們那時候在一起，對嗎？
Are you here to ask me that?
妳來就是要問我這個？
I once asked you the same question. Why did you say no?
同樣的問題我問過你一次 你為什麼說沒有？
Because there wasn't much to it.
因為那沒什麼好說的
There wasn't?
沒有嗎？
No.
沒有
Nothing would change by digging up those memories.
要是我說有，有什麼差別嗎？
Forty-eight people died there.
那裡死了48個人
And countless people got hurt and rescued.
還有無數受傷和被救的人
You and I were just among them.
妳跟我只是其中兩個
What's special about it?
有什麼特別的？
We met there. Is that nothing?
我們在那裡認識的，那沒意義嗎？
Do I mean nothing to you?
對你，我沒任何意義嗎？
I was the only one who had feelings for you?
只是我單方面對你有感覺嗎？
You're a huge jerk.
你是個大混蛋
You led me on.
你讓我喜歡上你
I'm already annoyed by so much as it is.
我現在要煩的事情已經很多了
I don't have time to reminisce about the past. Go.
我沒時間緬懷過去，回去吧
Do whatever you want.
想幹嘛就幹嘛吧
Do you work on weekends too?
你週末也工作？
You weren't at home.
你不在家
When did you change your passcode?
你什麼時候改了密碼？
You should've called me.
妳應該先打電話的
Like you'd answer.
你會接嗎？
Take it easy.
別太拼命
Think of your dad.
想想你爸爸
What did he gain by working day and night?
他日日夜夜工作，有得到什麼嗎？
You should enjoy your life.
你應該享受你的人生
Date a girl.
去約會
By any chance, do you still have feelings for Yu-jin--
要是你對友真還有感覺…
Mother. You can do whatever you want.
母親，妳想做什麼都可以去做
I'm still my father's son.
我始終是父親的兒子
-But you're not his wife anymore. -Ju-won.
-但是妳已經不是他的妻子了 -周元
Don't go through this hassle again.
不要再為這件事煩心了
It's late. Go home.
很晚了，回家吧
Don't skip meals.
記得要定時吃飯
Why are you home so late?
妳怎麼這麼晚才回家？
What brings you here at this hour?
你這麼晚來這裡，有事嗎？
-I'm here to see you. -Me?
-我來看看妳 -看我？
You haven't come by recently.
妳最近都沒去我那裡
it's not like i used to go everyday.
好像我每天都會去似的
What's the matter?
有什麼事嗎？
I heard you work in Useok-dong.
我聽說妳在禹錫洞工作
Does your mom know?
妳媽知道嗎？
My guess was right.
我猜得沒錯
She'll be shocked if she finds out. Quit if it's nothing important.
要是她知道，她會很震驚 如果不是很重要，就把工作辭掉吧
How can I quit all of a sudden?
我怎麼可以突然辭職？
I can go there if I want.
我想去那裡就可以去
For what? It's not like you have fond memories of the place.
為了什麼？妳對那個地方 又不是有美好的回憶
What about you?
那你呢？
Why do you sell noodles there?
你幹嘛在那裡賣麵？
Your mom still drinks, right?
妳媽還有在喝酒吧？
Heat this up for her in the morning.
明天早上把這個熱給她吃
Are you leaving without seeing her?
你還沒見到她就要走了嗎？
She'd be upset if she saw me.
看到我，她會不高興
Don't tell her I came by.
不要告訴她我來過
-Don't come close to me. -We could freeze to death.
-不要靠近我 -我們會凍死
Do you know what time it is?
妳知道幾點了嗎？
Keep the volume down, Mom.
把電視關小聲點，媽
Speak for yourself. Why are you home so late?
說妳自己吧，妳幹嘛這麼晚回家？
You're acting strange these days.
妳最近的表現很奇怪
You go out often and come home late.
經常出去，還很晚回家
Is the old lady okay?
那個老太太還好嗎？
No.
不好
Any children?
有孩子嗎？
Does she have someone to look after her?
有人照顧她嗎？
Yes.
有
Yes?
有嗎？
Yes. She has a very nice person to look after her.
有，她有一個非常好的人在照顧她
He got caught anyways.
他終於被我逮到了
He wasn't disappointed in you.
他不是對妳感到失望
It's because he thinks he's pathetic.
那是因為他覺得自己很可悲
If he's keeping his distance, it means he cherishes you that much.
要是他跟妳保持距離 那是因為他非常珍惜妳
GALAXY INN
（銀河客棧）
You do whatever you want.
你想幹嘛就幹嘛吧
I'll do the same.
我也會這麼做
Aren't you going?
你不走嗎？
What?
幹嘛？
-What's that? -You know what it is.
-那是什麼？ -你知道是什麼
You always get beaten by someone.
你總是被人打
I wasn't beaten this time. I just got hurt at work.
這一次我沒被打，是工作時受的傷
Then don't get hurt. It's painful.
那就不要受傷，那很痛
You're a busybody.
妳很雞婆
-Do you do this to anyone? -You're not just anyone.
-妳對任何人都這樣嗎？ -你又不是任何人
I'm late. I'll see you later.
我遲到了，等會見
For what?
要幹嘛？
-Yes. -This space here.
這裡的空間
Yes, do it like this. The wooden part should be like this.
對，要這樣做，有木板的部分應該要這樣
What did Mr. Lee say? When is he coming back to the site?
李先生怎麼說？他什麼時候要回工地？
I don't know.
不知道
Don't tell me you haven't met him yet.
別跟我說妳還沒見到他
You said you didn't fight.
妳說過你們沒有吵架
Why do I have to tell you what happens between him and me?
我為什麼要告訴妳我跟他之間發生的事？
If things work out between you two, you won't steal what's mine.
如果你們兩個發展順利 妳就不會搶走我的男人
-Sorry? -Mr. Seo has feelings for you.
-妳說什麼？ -徐先生對妳有意思
And I still have feelings for Mr. Seo.
而我對他還有感覺
Let's not make things more complicated.
我們不要把事情搞得更複雜吧
I like Mr. Seo too.
我也喜歡徐先生
Everyone in this office likes him.
辦公室裡的每一個人都喜歡他
He's a good person.
他是個好人
So you don't have to be bothered by me.
所以妳不需要因為我而困擾
What about Mr. Lee Gang-du?
那麼李康斗呢？
Is he also a good colleague of yours?
他也是妳的一個很好的同事嗎？
He's different.
他不一樣
When he's not around, I get curious, worried and anxious.
他不在我身邊時，我會好奇、擔心和焦慮
Any more questions?
還有別的問題嗎？
That was a satisfactory answer. You may leave.
那個回答夠好了，妳可以離開了
-What are you doing? -I can't have you.
-妳在幹嘛？ -我得不到你
No one else should either.
別人也別想得到
You know I'm mean.
你知道我的意思
But I just wasted my time.
但是我只是浪費時間
What are you doing?
妳在幹嘛？
I'm getting older.
我老了
And I'm getting uglier.
也變醜了
No, you're not. You're still pretty.
不，才不是，妳還是很漂亮
Mun-su, I heard Mr. Seo and Ms. Jung didn't just simply break up.
文秀，聽說徐先生和鄭小姐 不是那麼簡單就分手的
Mr. Seo's mother and Ms. Jung's father got remarried to each other,
徐先生的母親和鄭小姐的父親 他們兩個結婚了
so they became a family.
所以他們成了一家人
Family?
家人？
If they're a family…
如果他們是家人…
They're just like Romeo and Juliet. How can I beat that?
他們就像是羅密歐與茱麗葉 我怎麼能打敗鄭小姐呢？
SEONGJI PRINTING
（晟記印刷）
GANG-DU, INCOMING CALL
（康斗來電）
Darn it.
該死的
-When did you come back? -Is Granny here?
-你什麼時候回來的？ -老奶奶在這裡嗎？
Why would she come here?
她怎麼會來這裡？
She's driving me crazy. Where did she go?
她讓我快抓狂了，她到底去了哪裡？
Why worry about her? She's not reckless. Why did you get on the fishing boat?
幹嘛擔心她？她不是魯莽的人 你為什麼去漁船工作？
Did you know that she was sick too?
妳也已經知道她生病的事嗎？
I noticed it,
我有注意到
but I heard about it only a few days ago.
但我是幾天前才聽說的
She keeps refusing to go to the hospital, right?
她一直拒絕去醫院，對嗎？
Your sister must've told you already.
你妹妹一定都跟你說了
If her surgery goes wrong, she won't recognize any of us.
要是手術出了問題 她就誰也都認不出來了
Who cares if she doesn't recognize us?
誰在乎她認不認得我們？
What's wrong with losing her memory? We need to save her life first!
失去記憶又怎麼了？我們首先要救她的命
Don't act like this to Mama!
不要在我面前無理取鬧
Don't you know who's actually suffering?
你不知道真正痛苦的人是誰嗎？
Darn it.
該死的
I understand you're scared.
我知道你很害怕
But we can't selfishly force her to live a hollow existence.
但是我們不能強迫她帶著空殼繼續活著
Show her how you feel.
讓她知道你的感受
But don't press her.
但是不要給她壓力
You're calm. That's good.
妳很冷靜，那樣很好
Do what you want.
去做妳想做的吧
I'll drag her to the hospital if I must.
我會把她送去醫院
Just wait for her at her store! She'll come back!
你在她店裡等她就好，她會回來的
Give me one too.
也給我一根
That startled me.
嚇死我了
You'll smoke even if I stop you, so just smoke to your heart's content.
就算我勸妳，妳還是會抽 那就抽到妳滿足為止吧
Where have you been? I've been looking all over for you.
妳去了哪裡？我到處找妳
Stop following me around. Just go see Mun-su instead.
不要跟著我，去找文秀
What an idiot.
真是個白癡
Why are you avoiding her?
你為什麼躲著她？
Do you have no confidence in yourself?
你沒自信嗎？
No, I don't.
我沒有
Why not? What do you not like about yourself?
為什麼沒有？你不喜歡自己的哪裡？
What are you saying? Look at me.
妳在說什麼？妳看看我
I can't afford to like someone right now.
我現在還沒有資格喜歡上別人
I'm not talking about your circumstances. I'm asking how you feel.
我說的不是你的狀態，我問的是你的感受
What a crazy punk.
真是個神經病的小混混
Even while I was worried when I heard you were sick,
聽到妳生病了，我很擔心
I was happy I got to come back and see Mun-su again. I'm a crazy jerk.
但是同時我很開心再看到文秀 我是個瘋掉了的笨蛋
I'm glad my illness was useful.
我很高興我的病有用處
Jeez.
天啊
I wish I were an attractive person.
我真希望我是個很有魅力的人
You idiot. That's not for you to decide. It's all for Mun-su to decide.
你這個白癡，這不是由你決定的 是文秀要決定的
Goodness. Don't try to act cool, because that's so unlike you.
天啊，不要假裝你很酷 因為那樣太不像你了
Don't be intimidated. That doesn't suit you at all.
不要膽怯退縮，那樣完全不適合你
Good.
好啊
Continue to criticize me and adore me like this.
繼續像這樣批評我和疼我
You have a lot of things to do.
妳還有很多事要做
-Let's go to the hospital tomorrow. -What the heck? Don't waste your time.
-明天一起去醫院吧 -搞什麼？不要浪費你的時間
We won't know whether it's a waste of time unless we go there.
我們不知道是不是浪費時間 去了那裡才會知道
Let's go. All right? Or I'll carry you there on my back.
我們去吧，好嗎？ 要不然我會背著妳去那裡
Forget it. It won't do me any good.
算了吧，那對我沒好處
It'll do me good! All right?
對我有好處，懂嗎？
Please do me a favor. Will you?
請妳幫我一個忙，可以嗎？
Please, Granny!
拜託了，老奶奶
GALAXY INN
（銀河客棧）
Were you disappointed to not see me?
很失望嗎？
How far are you going to go?
妳還想要跟到哪裡？
It's not the first time.
又不是第一次
Why are you stopping me?
你幹嘛阻止我？
You were happy to see me earlier.
你剛剛很開心見到我
I was? When?
有嗎？什麼時候？
Come on. I saw your eyes get smaller.
拜託，我看到你的眼睛瞇起來了
You definitely smiled.
你肯定是笑了
You're talking nonsense.
妳在瞎扯
I have small eyes.
我的眼睛本來就很小
Leave. I want to go to sleep.
走吧，我想去睡覺了
Did you see Granny?
你去看老奶奶了嗎？
Was it hard?
你非常難過嗎？
Then go to sleep.
那就去睡吧
Don't think about anything. Just sleep tight.
什麼都別想，好好睡就好
I'll come again tomorrow.
我明天會再來
I'm going to come see you tomorrow, the day after that and the day after that.
明天、後天、大後天，我都會來看你
I'm going to come until I fall out of love with you.
我會一直來，直到我不再愛你為止
Oh. Gang-du.
康斗
I brought this to read it with you.
我帶了這本書要跟你一起看
A book?
一本書？
Good job.
很好
Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
-I heard you were sick. -You're back, so I'm okay now.
-我聽說你病了 -你回來了，所以我現在好了
That's a relief.
那我就放心了
Wait. Leave the light on.
等等，不要關燈
I don't like darkness.
我不喜歡黑暗
Are you scared?
你害怕嗎？
Do you want me to read this right next to you?
你要我讀故事給你聽嗎？
Then you won't be scared.
那你就不會害怕了
-Sang-man. -Yes?
-相萬 -怎樣？
Promise me you'll live longer than I do.
我希望你活得比我還久
I don't want to live a long life alone.
我不要獨自一個人活很久
Can we both live long?
我們可以一起活很久嗎？
Sure. Let's do that.
當然，那就一起活很久吧
Go to bed, Gang-du.
睡覺吧，康斗
I'll read this to you until you fall asleep.
我會讀故事給你聽，直到你睡著為止
"Madame Gyeongwon hugged him from behind, making nasal sounds.
“卿瑗太太從後面緊抱著他 發出陣陣嗯嗯聲
And Gwanjachu felt her body pressing against his back.
光州感覺到她的身體壓在他的背上
That made him tremble.
讓他顫抖了起來
'Oh, if only I were ten years younger.
‘要是我再年輕十歲就好了
Then I would've made love to her all night long.'"
那我就會一整晚都跟她做愛
-"Oh, Madame." -Sang-man.
-太太‘” -相萬
Are you sure you want me to go to sleep?
你真的是要我睡覺嗎？
Gang-du is different.
康斗不一樣
When he's not around, I get curious, worried and anxious.
他不在我身邊時，我會好奇、擔心和焦慮
I told you we can go another time. Why are you making a fuss first thing?
我跟你說了我們可以改天再去 你幹嘛要小題大作？
When? It's already been a week.
什麼時候？都已經一個禮拜了
You can only chew on one side. And even hot water makes your teeth ache.
妳只能用一邊咬東西 連喝熱水都會讓妳牙痛
Then you could just take me to any clinic nearby.
那你可以帶我去附近的診所就好
While you're at it, get a checkup too.
既然是去看牙醫，那就檢查一下吧
It's strange that you say your jaw hurts, not your throat, whenever you yell at me.
每次妳對我喊叫，妳都說下巴很痛 而不是喉嚨痛，這很奇怪
You should take good care of your jaw.
妳應該要照顧好妳的下巴
When I dislocated mine, I didn't get proper treatment.
我下巴脫臼時，沒有接受適當的治療
And I still suffer.
到現在還會痛
What happened to your jaw?
你的下巴怎麼了？
My uncle beat me a lot when I was younger.
小時候，我的叔叔經常打我
Why do you smile when you talk about such a thing? It makes me feel bad.
說到這種事，你為什麼還笑？ 這讓我感覺很難過
Should I cry then?
那我應該哭嗎？
I'm okay now.
我現在沒事了
He passed away last year.
他去年過世了
This was his car.
這原本是他的車
MOKSAN CITY HOSPITAL
（木山市立醫院）
CERTIFIED BY MINISTRY OF HEALTH AND WELFARE
（獲衛生與福利部認證醫院）
Take this away.
把這個拿走
It tastes so bland to me.
對我來說太清淡了
You hate everything that's healthy.
健康的食物妳都不喜歡
Pick up the spoon. What are you doing? Don't waste food.
拿起湯匙繼續吃，妳要幹嘛？ 一定要把食物吃完
The spinach and quail eggs look good.
菠菜和鵪鶉蛋看起來很好吃
Granny.
老奶奶
Why are you here?
妳來做什麼？
I asked her to come.
是我叫她來的
You didn't finish your food. Shall I open this for you?
妳沒吃完妳的午餐，要幫妳打開這個嗎？
I lost my appetite. Later.
我沒胃口了，等一下吧
What? When did you two get so close?
是怎樣？妳們什麼時候這麼熟了？
Be quiet. We need to treat our guests nicely.
別說話，我們要好好款待我們的客人
Why are you sitting still like that?
你怎麼那樣呆呆地坐著？
Are you a refugee or what?
妳是難民還是怎樣？
They say, "People gather around hospitable houses." Keep that in mind.
他們說：“好客的房子會有人聚集” 你要記住這句話
Give them to her.
給她一些
Thank you.
謝謝妳
Don't thank me for that.
不要謝我
I'll be grateful if you enjoy the food.
要是妳喜歡吃，我會很高興
Oh, it's delicious.
太好吃了
-Oh, Mr. Rooftop! -Oh, hello.
-屋頂先生 -你們好
What brings you here?
你怎麼會在這裡？
It's done. Do you like the color?
好了，妳喜歡那個顏色嗎？
I wish it were more glittery.
我希望能更閃亮一點
This is good enough.
但這已經夠好看了
-I'll change the color tomorrow. -Okay.
-我明天要換顏色 -好的
Paint her nails too.
妳也幫她擦指甲油吧
She looks more depressed than I do.
她看起來比我還要沮喪
No, I'm fine.
不，不用了
I'm really fine.
真的不用了
This one? Let's go with this one.
這個顏色嗎？就用這個吧
Gang-du.
康斗
-Oh. -Hello, Granny.
-是你們 -妳好，老奶奶
What are you doing here?
妳來這裡幹嘛？
Ms. Kim is so dense that she didn't know her molar had cracked.
金小姐太遲鈍了 她都不知道自己的臼齒裂了
-I brought her here. -How did you crack it?
-我帶她來的 -妳是怎麼弄裂的？
Gang-du. You've become tougher. But you still have a boyish face.
康斗，你看起來比較堅強了 但是你還是有張孩子氣的臉
The contrast is what makes him attractive.
這種對比是他吸引人的地方
This is my friend. Say hello.
這是我的朋友，打聲招呼吧
Nice to meet you. I'm Kim Wan-jin, her friend.
很高興認識妳，我是金婉珍，她的朋友
-She draws comics. -Oh.
-她是畫漫畫的 -是啊
Granny. Don't we look alike?
老奶奶，我們兩個長得很像，對吧？
You're more handsome.
你比較帥
Really?
真的嗎？
Your fingernails are beautiful.
妳的指甲好漂亮
-Did you paint them for her? -Yes.
-是妳幫她塗的嗎？ -對啊
Can you paint mine too?
妳也可以幫我塗嗎？
Pick a color.
選個顏色吧
This one.
這個
It'd be fun to change the color every day.
每天都換顏色會很好玩 妳也選一個顏色吧
Please move.
麻煩讓開一下
Gang-du's sister?
康斗的妹妹？
You look like your brother. How pretty.
妳跟妳哥很像，多漂亮啊
We've met before, right?
我們之前見過吧？
Hi.
妳好
Oh, my. You have many grandchildren. You're so blessed.
天哪，妳有好多孫子女，妳真有福氣
It looks nice.
看起來很幸福
Yes, I'm very blessed.
沒錯，我很有福氣
Talk like you always do. What's with the way you talk?
用妳平常的語氣說話 妳這樣客氣說話是怎樣？
Hey, I'm thirsty. Get me a soda.
喂，我口渴了，幫我拿可樂
You're asking for a soda in a hospital? Man, you're just like a child.
妳在醫院要求喝可樂？ 天啊，妳就跟個小孩一樣
Here you go. This is the last one.
給妳，這是最後一罐了
Is it refreshing?
很清涼吧？
I like soda too.
我也喜歡可樂
I hope you'll get a husband soon.
我希望妳很快就會嫁出去
The kids are listening.
這些小孩都聽到了啦
She actually likes it.
她其實很喜歡這樣
-I know. -You can't fool me.
-我知道 -妳騙不了我
Granny said
老奶奶說
life is a repetition of regrets and failures.
人生就是不斷重複的悔恨和失敗
I sarcastically asked
我很諷刺地問她說
what's the point of living.
那活著有什麼意義？
Granny said
老奶奶說
it's to regret and fail more wonderfully…
就是要懊悔和更精彩地去經歷失敗
and advised me not to get intimidated.
她還勸我不要膽怯退縮
-Just until the bus comes. -What?
-只到公車來了為止 -什麼？
-Let's stay like this. -You're heavy.
-我們就這樣站著吧 -你很重
Endure it.
妳忍耐一下吧
You're working hard to be cute.
妳很努力打扮自己
Look at me, Mun-su. Gang-du bought me a suit…
看看我，文秀，康斗買了西裝給我…
Go ahead. Finish what you were doing.
繼續吧，把你們在做的事做完吧
Save her. You did all that studying to save people's lives.
救救她，你們用功讀書 不就是為了救人嗎？
So how come you're doing nothing?
你們為什麼什麼都沒做？
Let go of me and do something, you jerks!
放開我去做點什麼，你們這些混蛋
When a person dies,
人死了以後
they go back to when they were the prettiest, so don't worry.
會回到他們最漂亮的樣子 所以妳不要擔心
Don't pretend you don't know me when we meet again.
我們再遇見時，不要不理我
Just cuss me out.
妳只要對著我亂罵
You shouldn't ignore me.
妳不能不理我